A Guide to the Burke, Virginia Collection, 1937-2015
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Burke, Virginia Collection, 1937-2015
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 03-03
.5 linear feet
The Burke, Virginia Collection consists of 0.5 linear feet and spans the years 1937-2015 consisting of reports, correspondence, newspaper clippings, newsletters, brochures, pamphlets, photocopies, framed needlework art, a commemorative pin, and a hand drawn map.
Virginia Room Staff
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
The Virginia Room staff artificially created this collection over a period of time. Nan Netherton donated several items in this collection in March 1993 and staff continue to add to it.
Historical and Biographical Information
Burke, Virginia is named after Col. Silas Burke (1796-1854) who lived in Fairfax County near the Ravensworth plantation of the Fitzhughs, the location of which today is known as the Silas Burke House. In 1854, the area became known as “Burke’s Station” after Silas Burke, then a director for the Orange and Alexandria Railroad, donated land for the right of way and a railroad station. During the Civil War, the area saw heavy action. Burke’s notable claim to fame occurred on December 28, 1862 when Confederate General J.E.B. Stuart raided Burke’s Station, seized supplies and the telegraph office, and sent a telegram to Union Quartermaster General Montgomery C. Meigs complaining of the poor quality of mules he had captured.
After the war, Burke remained a sleepy town until June 13, 1951, when the Justice Department posted public notices in the Burke post office announcing that the government condemned 4,520 acres of land in the Burke area for the new Washington airport. The citizens fought a successful battle against the airport’s construction and ultimately the government relocated the airport to Chantilly, Va where it is today known as Dulles International Airport. Since then, Burke has grown significantly with the construction of housing subdivisions and land development.
Scope and Content
The Burke, Virginia Collection consists of 0.5 linear feet and spans the years 1937-2015 consisting of reports, correspondence, newspaper clippings, newsletters, brochures, pamphlets, photocopies, framed needlework art, a commemorative pin, and a hand drawn map. Subjects include the history of Burke, Virginia, Burke Centre Conservancy, and the Copperthite Racetrack.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
MSS 06-73 Ralph Raney Papers on Silas Burke Study
MSS 06-74 Rosanne S. Berkenstock Papers on Burke Centre Study
None
Index Terms
Burke, Virginia - History; Burke Centre Conservancy; Copperthite Racetrack
Container List
- “The Burke Airport Issue: A Case Study in Public Policy and Citizen Opposition” by Kevin L. Kramer [Gift of Nan Netherton, March 1993], 1975 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Broadside, “Government Auction of Burke, VA. Airport Site”, June 13, 1959 (photocopy) [Gift of Nan Netherton, March 1993], Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newspaper clipping, “Four Views of Burke Airport Site”, Washington Times-Herald, 1951 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Newspaper, Annandale Free Press Special Supplement on Kings Park Community, Burke, VA., 1966 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- “Copperthite Racetrack” by Susan Bujan [Gift of Nan Netherton, March 1993], Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- “Henry Copperthite and the Burke Race Track” by Laura Reilly, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- “Burke’s Station” by Col. Arthur John Cornelson, 1969 August 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence of Hazel Davis, Memorandum on Early History of Burke, Virginia, 1937, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Burke Commons Civic Association Newsletters, “Historical Bits of Burke” by Owen J. Remington, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Pamphlet, “An Introduction To The History of The Burke Centre Area”, 1977 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Burke Centre Conservancy, Covenants and Articles of Incorporation [Gift of Nan Netherton, March 1993], 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Burke Centre promotional folder and map, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Terra Centre Elementary School promotional architectural brochures [Gift of Nan Netherton, March 1993], 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Map of Burke (hand drawn, author unknown), Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Newspaper clipping, “Site of New Washington Airport”, Washington Post, 1951 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Marriage certificate, Benjamin Hampton and Fannie Peyton at Burke’s Station, 1898 (photocopy), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Burke Cove condominiums promotional brochure, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Pin, Burke Centre Conservancy 25th Anniversary, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Framed needlepoint artwork of Burke Centre logo, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)